Guide to the Bernard Perlin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bernard Perlin papers
1940-2006
YCAL MSS 849
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
21.09
(28 boxes)
Correspondence, artwork, photographs, negatives, and other printed material.
Perlin, Bernard, 1918-2014
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 34 (videocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence; artwork, including sketchbooks and two busts; photographs and negatives; printed material, including clippings; and other related papers documenting the life and work of the artist Bernard Perlin. Material pertaining to Perlin's work creating propaganda art as an artist-correspondent for Fortune and Life magazines during the Second World War is present, as is material documenting his later landscape and figurative painting.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: February 2006 Acquisition, May 2007 Acquisition, September 2007 Acquisition, and November 2010 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Biographical / Historical
Bernard Perlin (1918-2014) was an American painter and an artist-correspondent for Life and Fortune magazines during World War II. He began working as an artist in 1938, when he received a fellowship to paint in Poland; he then painted murals for the United States Treasury Department and the United States Maritime Commission.
Fortune (New York, N.Y.); Artists -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda; Art, American -- 20th Century; War correspondents -- United States; Sketchbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Busts (figures) -- United States -- 20th Century; Sculpture (visual work) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Negatives -- United States -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; War correspondents -- United States -- 20th Century; Perlin, Bernard, 1918-2014
- February 2006 Acquisition, 1940-2005; Series I; 19.09; (25 boxes) + 2 art, 4 broadsides
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence; artwork, including sketchbooks and 2 busts; photographs and negatives; printed material, including clippings; and other papers by or relating to Bernard Perlin.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 851
  Arrangement
  This portion of the collection is organized into ten series: Correspondence, 1940-2005; Diaries, Notebooks, and Calendars, 1945-2005; Biographical and Financial Papers, 1940-2002; Photographs, 1945-2001; Research Files on Other Artists, 1991-2002; Papers Relating to Perlin's Artwork, 1942-1990; Printed Material and Clippings, 1944-2005; Memorabilia and Audiovisual Material, 1993, 1995; Oversize, 1952-1995; Oversize Folders, 1943.
  - Correspondence
    - Crump, Jim, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Dreyfus, J.R., undated (Box 1)
    - Jelenski, Konstanty, 1951-1997 (Box 1)
    - Long, Arthur, 1963-1976 (Box 1)
    - Pecker, Joe, 1993-2005; 2 (Box 1)
    - Wescott, Glenway and "B.P. letters", 1940-1956; 2 (Box 1)
    - Wood, Dick, 1964-1970; 4 (Box 1)
    - Family, 1940-1987; 10 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1958-1994; 3 (Box 1)
    - Christmas cards, 1990-2003; 24 (Box 2)
    - Christmas cards, 2004-2005; 3 (Box 3)
    - Personal
      - Personal, 1960-1985, undated; 13 (Box 3)
        Includes postcards and greeting cards.
      - Personal, 1942-2002; 21 (Box 4)
      - Postcards, 1961-1989, undated; 6 (Box 5)
  - Diaries, Notebooks, and Calendars
    - Diaries
      - 1965-1966 (Box 5)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 5)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 5)
      - 1971 (Box 5)
    - Notebooks, 1945, 1971, undated (Box 5)
    - Calendars
      - 1961, 1967, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - 1981-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1990-1995 (Box 5)
      - 1997-1999, 2001-2002, 2004-2005 (Box 5)
    - Record books (phone numbers, addresses, calendars, and other records)
      - Income/expenses/exhibit list (Box 5)
      - Phone numbers and miscellaneous, 1956-1969; 7 (Box 6)
      - Record books, 1973-1975, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Sketchbooks, 8 (Box 7)
  - Sketchbooks and sketches, undated; 5 (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - Sketchbooks, undated; 5 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Biographical and Financial Papers
    - Biographical information, 1940-1996; 4 (Box 7)
    - Financial papers, 1953-2002; 3
      Includes informations on Europe trips.
    - Unsorted financial papers, clippings, and correspondence, 1940-2000; 2 (Box 7)
  - Photographs
    - George Platt Lynes photographs of Orson Welles, undated (Box 8)
    - George Platt Lynes photographs from envelope bearing war correspondence censor's stamp, undated; 4 (Box 8)
    - Photographs by George Platt Lynes, undated; 20 (Box 8)
    - George Platt Lynes related material, 1982, undated; 4 (Box 8)
    - Japanese surrender U.S.S. Missouri; portrait of David Douglas Duncan, 1945 (Box 8)
    - Italian paintings, 1948-1952 (Box 8)
    - Saba, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Baily party, 2001 February (Box 8)
    - Terry Abbott and Bear, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Skyline, near Monticello, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Mexico, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Sprite, undated (Box 8)
    - Africa, 1987-1988; 3 (Box 8)
    - Virginia: Charlottesville, Monticello, undated (Box 9)
    - Family, 1961-1966, undated (Box 9)
    - California, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Wisteria, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Africa, undated (Box 9)
    - Greenhouse, undated (Box 9)
    - Puerto Rico, 1976 (Box 9)
    - "Xmas Zucker", 1973 (Box 9)
    - Bud's house, Sprite, undated (Box 9)
    - Perlin at waterfall, Africa, 1988-1999 (Box 9)
    - California, Yosemite, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Winter in Connecticut, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Sprite at home, 1981-1987 (Box 9)
    - California and Denver, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Bermuda, 1975 (Box 9)
    - New Year's Eve and South Carolina, 1974, 1975 February (Box 9)
    - Bud's house, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
    - Unsorted, undated; 13 (Box 9)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 9)
    - Perlin aboard the U.S.S. Missouri, 1945 (Box 9)
  - Research Files on Other Artists
    - Kirstein, 1999 (Box 10)
    - Henry Koerner, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Exhibit brochures, 1996-2000 (Box 10)
    - Cadmus, 2000-2002 (Box 10)
    - Irvin Milken eulogy, 2002 (Box 10)
    - Glenway Wescott, 1991 (Box 10)
    - Jerry Rosco, 2000 (Box 10)
    - Gellhorn, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Papers Relating to Perlin's Artwork
    - Photocopies of Perlin's art, 1983 (Box 10)
    - Harper's magazine article with drawings by Perlin, 1959 April (Box 10)
    - Gallery and museum fliers and brochures, 1952-1999; 14 (Box 10)
    - Posters
      - "Americans Will Always Fight for Liberty", 1943; 5 (Box 11)
      - "AMERICANS will always fight for liberty", poster, 1943 (Box 30 (Broadside))
      - "You Make It Right, They'll Make It Fight", 1942 (Box 11)
      - "You Make it RIGHT... They'll make it FIGHT", poster, 1942 (Box 31 (Broadside))
      - "Let 'em Have It", 1943 (Box 11)
      - "Avenge December 7th", 1942; 2 (Box 11)
    - Photographs of Perlin's paintings, 9 (Box 11)
    - Photographs of Perlin's drawings (Box 11)
    - Animal Clinic of Danbury medical records, 1990 (Box 11)
    - Photographs of exhibitions, undated; 2 (Box 11)
    - Spokane presentation (Box 11)
    - Perlin's artwork (Box 11)
    - Slides (Box 11)
    - Negatives, 4 (Box 11)
  - Printed Material and Clippings
    - PWA Coalition Newsletter, 1989 February (Box 11)
    - ARTnews, 1970 (Box 11)
    - Map and photographs of the moon, undated (Box 11)
    - New York City Ballet, Dance Index, American Ballet, and clippings relating to George Platt Lynes photography, 1944-1999 (Box 11)
    - "Criticisms, etc.", clippings, 1955-1983; 5 (Box 11)
    - "Chuck's" obituary, 2002 October 5 (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 1952-1996; 3 (Box 12)
    - Exhibition brochures, 1950-1997; 3 (Box 12)
    - Unsorted brochures, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
    - Plant and animal prints, undated (Box 12)
    - The Eye of Man by Selden Rodman, 1955 (Box 12)
    - Conversations with Artists by Selden Rodman, 1957 (Box 12)
    - Fortune, 1960 March; 2 (Box 12)
    - Fortune, 1964 June (Box 12)
    - The New Yorker, 1996 June 17 (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 1953, 1985-1999; 3 (Box 12)
    - Clippings and related correspondence, 1997 (Box 12)
    - Owner's manuals, undated (Box 12)
    - Clippings, notes, brochures as grouped by Perlin, 1969-1988; 3 (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 1997-2000 (Box 12)
    - Campaign for NYC Ballet, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Balanchine 100, 2003 (Box 13)
    - NYC Ballet clippings, 1993-1998 (Box 13)
    - The Campaign for NYC Ballet, 2001-2005 (Box 13)
    - NYC Ballet News, 2000-2005 (Box 13)
    - NYC Ballet, 1998 Winter-2005 Spring (Box 13)
    - ACLS, 1983-1997 (Box 13)
    - Clippings, 1995-2004 (Box 13)
  - Memorabilia and Audiovisual Material
    - Objects, 4 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Luggage tags, undated (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Chess set, undated (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Boxes of trinkets, undated; 3 (Box 14 (Oversize))
    - Mementos from Africa, undated (Box 15 (Oversize))
      Includes keys, unidentified seals, rocks, war correspondent badges, and a flag. A razor blade, metal pen nib, and unidentified object were removed from the collection, due to preservation concerns; these items are documented with photographic surrogates in the box.
    - Bust (Box 16 (Art))
    - Bust (Box 17 (Art))
    - Slides (Box 18)
    - Negatives, enclosed in glass, undated (Box 18)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 18)
    - VHS cassettes
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - "London-Sainsbury Launch", undated; YCALMSS849_0001; 1; 00:39:35; PAL to NTSC conversion (Box 34 (Restricted Fragile), Item barcode 39002102317451)
      - "World War II Journalists," Bill Mauldin, Bernard Palin, William Shirer, Robert St. John, John Hersey, for the National Portrait Gallery, 1993; YCALMSS849_0002; 1; 00:38:32 (Box 34 (Restricted Fragile), Item barcode 39002102317469)
      - Sainsbury's Pictures for Schools, Art Classics, BBC2, 1995; YCALMSS849_0003; 1; 00:37:20 (Box 34 (Restricted Fragile), Item barcode 39002102317477)
    - Postcards, 8 (Box 18)
  - Oversize
    - Photocopy of Perlin painting, undated (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Calendar, undated (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Clippings, undated (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Creatis and Fine Photography, 1984 (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - Woman's Home Companion, 1955 September (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - The Inlander, 1995 November 1-7 (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - Print, "The Sermon on the Mount", undated (Box 22 (Oversize))
    - Redbook, 1952 November (Box 23 (Oversize))
    - Fortune, Woman's Home Companion, The Saturday Evening Post, 1964 June, 1955 September, 1963 March (Box 23 (Oversize))
    - Fortune, 1961 December (Box 23 (Oversize))
    - Fortune, 1961 August (Box 23 (Oversize))
    - Fortune, 1960 March (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Fortune, July 1958, 1950 April, January 1950 (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Loose pages from Fortune, circa 1960; 2 (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Clippings, 4 (Box 25 (Oversize))
    - Clippings, 5 (Box 26 (Oversize))
    - Scrapbook, 1 (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Calendar (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Sketches (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - Oversize Folders
    - "AMERICANS will always fight for liberty", original artwork, 1943 (Box 28 (Broadside))
    - "Chicago- '63", pen and ink sketch, undated (Box 29 (Broadside))
- May 2007 Acquisition, 1961-1961; Series II; 1
  Former call number: Uncat ZA File 710
  - Letter from Glenway Wescott to Bernard Perlin, autograph manuscript, signed, 1961 April 17 (Box 18)
- September 2007 Acquisition, 1976-2006; Series III; 1; (1 box)
  Telephone log books, printed material, including clippings, and computer printouts.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 970
  This portion of the collection is arranged chronologically.
  - Telephone log books, 1976-2004; 9 (Box 32)
  - Calendar, 2006 (Box 32)
  - Printed material and clippings, 2005-2006 (Box 32)
- November 2010 Acquisition, undated; Series IV; 1; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 1250
  - Pillow, designed by Bernard Perlin with embroidery by George Platt Lynes and Russell Lynes., undated (Box 33)